https://youtu.be/nqH2ipzFz_A
anlynguyenphuoc_gtc_Y2VjYm 07/09/2016
SPEAKER: To help you get started with Spark
Để giúp bạn bắt đầu với Spark
and to make you a better Spark developer,
và trở thành nhà phát triển Spark thành thạo,
there's a lot of documentation and resources available.
có rất nhiều tài liệu có sẵn.
So the first place to start, always,
Vậy nơi đầu tiên để bắt đầu,
is with the Spark online documentation.
chính là tài liệu trực tuyến của Spark.
And you can find it at Spark.Apache.org/docs/latest,
Bạn có thể truy cập vào spark.apache.org/docs/latest
and then select Python from the API docs dropdown.
rồi chọn Python trong mục xổ xuống API docs
Another good source of information and examples
Một nguồn tham khảo có kèm ví dụ khác
is the Databrick's guide.
là hướng dẫn của Databricks. (Databricks Guide)
You can click on the question mark
Nhấp vào dấu chấm hỏi
and then click on Databrick's Guide.
sau đó nhấp vào Databricks Guide.
And browse the notebooks.
Rồi xem qua các bài học.
You can also copy the notebooks into your workspace
Bạn có thể sao chép chúng vào môi trường làm việc
and then run the examples that are in those notebooks.
và chạy các ví dụ trong các bài học đó.
Another good resource is the technical blogs.
Một nguồn tham khảo tốt khác chính là các blog kỹ thuật
And here are three technical blogs
Đây là ba blog kỹ thuật
that you might find interesting to read.
hẳn sẽ thú vị với bạn.
They'll oftentimes have news about what's
Chúng có tin tức mới về Spark, cũng như
upcoming for Spark, and also examples of performing
các ví dụ cách thực hành
common tasks using Sparks.
những mẫu việc thông thường bằng Spark.
Here are the blogs for Databricks,
Đây là blog của Databricks,
for Cloudera, and for IBM.
của Cloudera và IBM.
You can also find Spark on YouTube.
Bạn cũng có thể tìm Spark trên Youtube.
So check out the Apache Spark YouTube channel.
Hãy xem qua kênh Youtube Apache Spark
There is also a very large Spark community.
Ngoài ra còn có cộng đồng Spark khá lớn.
And you can find it by going to the Spark.Apache.org website,
Bạn có thể gia nhập bằng cách vào trang spark.apache.org
and going to community.html.
và đến community.html
And you'll see there are two sets of mailing lists.
Bạn sẽ thấy có hai nhóm danh sách email.
There are mailing lists for users,
Danh sách email cho người dùng,
and there are also mailing lists for developers.
và danh sách email cho nhà phát triển.
You can also see events and meet ups that are upcoming.
Ngoài ra có các sự kiện, các buổi họp mặt sắp diễn ra.
There is a very large Apache Spark meet up community.
Có một cộng đồng meet up về Apache Spark,
It has several hundred thousand members,
với vài trăm nghìn thành viên,
and hundreds of meet ups that occur around the globe.
và hàng trăm buổi họp mặt diễn ra khắp hành tinh.
So go to Spark.Meetup.com, and you can find out
Truy cập spark.meetup.com,
more about meet ups nearby.
bạn sẽ thấy các buổi họp mặt gần đây.
Databrick's forum, at Forums.Databricks.com,
Diễn đàn Databricks, forums.databricks.com,
is a community forum for Databricks users.
là diễn đàn dành cho cộng đồng người dùng Databricks.
So you'll find mostly Databrick specific questions and answers,
Vì vậy bạn sẽ thấy chủ yếu là các câu hỏi và câu trả lời về Databricks
and you'll find a few general Spark questions and answers
cùng một số câu hỏi, cũng như câu trả lời chung chung
also.
về Spark.
Spark Packages is a repository where you can find
Bạn có thể tìm trong kho dữ liệu Spark Packages
software packages for Spark.
các gói phần mềm cho Spark.
These are user provided and developed Spark extensions,
Chúng là các tiện ích mở rộng cho Spark, do người dùng viết ra và phát triển,
and they're rated by the community.
và được cộng đồng đánh giá.
So you can see which extensions are really good,
Do đó bạn sẽ nhận biết được tiện ích nào thật sự tốt,
and which extensions might need a little bit more work.
và tiện ích nào cần được cải thiện.
If you're really interested in how Spark works,
Nếu bạn thật sự hứng thú về cách hoạt động của Spark,
you can look at the GitHub repository.
hãy tìm đến kho dữ liệu GitHub.
Apache Spark is completely open source.
Apache Spark là mã nguồn mở hoàn toàn.
And so you can browse through the actual code
Vì thế bạn có thể xem những dòng code
that runs everything that you're using in Spark.
chạy mọi thứ có trong Spark.
For detailed explanations, read the comments
Các ghi chú (comment) có trong code
that are in the code.
sẽ giải thích chi tiết hơn.